<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The application of scripture. Or The maner how to vse the word to most edifying. By Thomas Granger preacher of the word at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston, in Lincolnshire</title>
            <author>Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114983</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850203</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850203</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15390</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15390)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1272:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The application of scripture. Or The maner how to vse the word to most edifying. By Thomas Granger preacher of the word at Botterwike in Holland, neere Boston, in Lincolnshire</title>
                  <author>Granger, Thomas, b. 1578.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Yuie lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15390:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15390:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE APPLICATION OF SCRIPTVRE. <hi>OR</hi> The maner how to vſe the Word <hi>to moſt edifying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By THOMAS GRANGER preacher of <hi>the word at</hi> Botterwike <hi>in</hi> Holland, neere <hi>Boſton,</hi> in Lincolnſhire.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>GOD IS MY HELPER</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pauier,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Yuie</hi> lane. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15390:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15390:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and vertuous Lady, the Lady IOAN LEVENTHORP, temporall, and eternall happineſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAME:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſincere conceit of your worthines, conſisting part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thoſe heauenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, wherewith the Lord hath beautified and adorned you, as ſolid wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, pietie, humilitie, ſinceritie in all things: herein ſhewing your ſelfe the expreſſe image of that worthy, and iudicious man <hi>Sir Iohn Brograue</hi> your Father; and chiefely in your Chriſtian loue towards all that loue God, and liue a godly life: euen theſe ſole conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:15390:3"/>
haue moued mee to dedicate this ſmall and worthleſſe worke to your Ladiſhip, which if it ſhall pleaſe you to accept as the Widowes mite, into the treaſury of your other Bookes, eſteeming it rather by the minde of the giuer, then valuing it by the weight of it ſelfe, you ſhall fully ſatisfie my deſire. The Lord conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtill his wonted goodneſſe, and louing kindneſſe towards you, who as he hath made you a ioyfull Mother of many faire children, and carefull of their vertuous education; ſo it would pleaſe his heauenly Maieſty to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill your ioy, in your latter daies, by beholding their vertuous courſes and deſired eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here in the earth; that in the end both you and they may reioyce together for euer in the promiſed <hi>Canaan,</hi> when your Arabian pilgrimage is here finiſhed. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Botterwike</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> neere <hi>Boſton</hi> in <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips<lb/>
in all dutie<lb/>
THOMAS GRANGER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15390:3"/>
            <head>THE APPLICATION OF SCRIPTVRE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. SAM. 12. 7.</bibl>
                  <p>Then ſaid <hi>Nathan</hi> to <hi>Dauid,</hi> Thou art the man.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Ing <hi>Dauid</hi> had prouoked the Lord to wrath by committing two grieuous ſinnes, Adultery, and Murther which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followeth the ſame by one meanes, or other. Therefore he ſent the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> to reproue him, and to denounce theſe iudgements againſt him. Firſt, that the ſword ſhould neuer depart from his houſe. Secondly, that his owne ſonne ſhould take his wiues from him. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the childe begotten in adultery ſhould die. Wherein we obſerue: firſt the iuſtice of God, in that he will puniſh ſinne, and the ſinnes of them eſpecially vpon whom he hath more plentifully poured his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits: And againe, the mercy of God, in that he will not ſuffer his children to lie in ſinne, and ſo to periſh by ſinne, but awaketh their conſciences and ſtirres
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15390:4"/>
them vp to repentance by correcting them, leaſt they ſhould periſh with the world. Out of his iuſtice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mixt with mercie, he ſent the Prophet, and the Prophet comming, propounded his ſinne by way of a parable, that not being blinded with partialitie, and ſelfe-loue (as all men are) he might giue righteous iudgement againſt himſelfe in the perſon of another. <hi>There were,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>two men in one citie, the one rich, and the other poore: the rich man had exceeding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſheepe, and oxen; but the poore had none at all, ſaue one little ſheepe which hee had bought, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vp, and it grew vp with him, and with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alſo, and did eate of his owne morſels, and dranke of his owne cuppe, and ſlept in his boſome, and was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him as his daughter. Now there came a ſtranger vnto the rich man, who refuſed to take of his owne ſheepe, and of his owne oxen to dreſſe for the ſtranger, that was come vnto him, but tooke the poore mans ſheepe and dreſſed it for the man, that was come vnto him.</hi> Hereupon <hi>Dauid</hi> maketh anſwer. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. He was exceeding wroth, and ſaid that the man which did that thing was the childe of death, and that hee ſhould reſtore the Lambe foureſold. In the <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Nathan</hi> maketh particular application.</p>
            <p>Thou art the man.</p>
            <p>From this practiſe of the Prophet, we learne that the true Prophets and Miniſters of Chriſt muſt make particular application of the word of the Lord, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of commandement; exhortation, admonition, reproofe, &amp;c. to thoſe to whom they are ſent, whether it be to a kingdome, to a particular people, or to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men, and though worldly men being ſtiffe-neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hard hearted, will not yeeld themſelues vnder the yoake of obedience, and are therefore alway rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to make reſiſtance, yet muſt wee know who hath ſent vs, both with promiſe of protection and reward
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15390:4"/>
for the faithfull diſcharge of our duties, and alſo with denuntiation of vengeance for our diſobedience, and rebellion. <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. 19. <hi>Speake all that I command thee;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 17. 19.</note>
               <hi>be not affraide of their faces, leaſt I deſtroy thee before them; they ſhall fight againſt thee, but ſhall not preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee, for I am with thee to deliuer thee.</hi> And in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place, <hi>Sonne of man, though they be rebellious, yet be not thou rebellious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this, we haue many examples to encourage vs hereunto. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 13. 14. Foure hundred Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <note place="margin">1 King. 22. 13. 14.</note>had propheſied victory to <hi>Ahas</hi> at <hi>Ramtoth Gile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad,</hi> and at <hi>Iehoſaphats</hi> requeſt, <hi>Micah</hi> the Prophet of the Lord was ſent for: the meſſenger aduiſed him (wiſely and diſcreetely as he ſuppoſed) to doe the like, but he anſwered, <hi>As the Lord liueth, whatſoeuer the Lord hath ſaid vnto me, that will I ſpeake.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18. 17. 18. <note place="margin">1. King. 18. 17. 18.</note>Thus faithfully alſo dealt <hi>Elias</hi> with him, <hi>It is not I that haue troubled Iſrael, but thou, and thy fathers houſe, in that ye haue forſaken the commandements of the Lord, and thou haſt followed Baalim.</hi> In the obiection of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab, verſ.</hi> 17. obſerue the nature of blinde and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſinners, they make the true Prophets and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters the cauſes of their calamities and plagues, whereas the cauſe is in themſelues, that refuſing inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and reformation, contemne and perſecute the ſeruants of God ſent vnto them, and deſpiſe the word of the Lord ſent by them. To this purpoſe, note well that ignorant and rebellious ſpeech of the high prieſts and Phariſees. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11. 48. <hi>If we let him thus alone, all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 48.</note>
               <hi>men will beleeue in him, and the Romanes will come, and take away both our place, and the Nation.</hi> Here you ſee, that they would make the Goſpell to be the cauſe of their vtter ouerthrow, and the ouerthrow of the Goſpell, to be the onely meanes of their, ſafetie. But theſe faithleſſe, and godleſſe polititians were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, for that which they feared came vpon them,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15390:5"/>
through the wrong auoiding thereof. In the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church, what euill ſoeuer happened to the citie or prouinces of Rome, whether famine, peſtilence, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, warres, vnſeaſonable weather, &amp;c. the Chriſtians were thought to be the cauſes thereof: whereupon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe great perſecution againſt them: yea, in theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent daies, many ignorant and blinde people doe yet thinke, that preaching makes the world ſo bad as it is: whereas indeede, it is the want of preaching, &amp; want of faith and obedience in them to the ſame, that maketh the word ſo bad, and which bringeth Gods iudgements vpon our heads, euen as the vnbeleefe and rebellion of the heathen againſt God and his people, brought thoſe heauie plagues of God vpon them, which they <note place="margin">2 King. 3. 13. 14.</note>imputed to the Chriſtians. In 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3. 13. 14. <hi>Iehoram</hi> and <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> and the king of <hi>Edom,</hi> entred warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of <hi>Moab</hi> for denying tribute to <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> King of Iſrael, and when they had no water in their iourney by the ſpace of ſeauen daies, they come to enquire of the Lord by <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this anſwere to the idolatrous King of Iſrael; <hi>What haue I to doe with thee? get thee to the Prophets of thy Father, and of thy Mother:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, thy heart is prophane and idolatrous, and thou not lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſerue the Lord, doeſt come to ſerue thine owne turne of the Lord, and of me: therefore, <hi>as the Lord of hoſts liueth, in whoſe ſight I ſtand, if it were</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3. 19.</note>
               <hi>not that I regard the preſence of Iehoſaphat, I would not haue looked towards thee, nor ſeene thee.</hi> Likewiſe in <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 19. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt reprooued <hi>Herod</hi> for his inceſt, and all his other euils. And the conſtancie and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">Act. 3. Act 7. 51. 52. Ier. 20. 3. 4. 5.</note>of <hi>Peter</hi> in the particular reproofe of the Iewes. <hi>Act.</hi> 3. of <hi>Steuen, Act.</hi> 7. 51 52. of <hi>Ieremie, Ier.</hi> 20. 3. 4. 5. yea, of all the Prophets, Apoſtles, and faithfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours ſince the beginning, may and ought to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs to the faithfull diſcharge of our duties herein.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15390:5"/>
For the further clearing of this point, foure things are to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the neceſſitie of particular application.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the perſon that is to make application in particular.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to whom it is to be made.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, how it is to be receiued, and taken.</p>
            <p>Application in particular, is neceſſary for diuers cauſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the ſound conuerſion of a ſinner. For men doe commonly receiue the word formally and hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically, being generally deliuered and taught, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more applying the ſame confuſedly, and vncertainely to all, or one to another, but none to himſelfe for his owne particular inſtruction, and reformation. In this caſe the word is made like a certaine medicine which <note place="margin">Dorneus.</note>ſome Phyſitions write of, that it will cure all diſeaſes, but when a man comes to take the ſame, he ſhall not finde himſelfe cured of any diſeaſe by it, but he is ſure to be in great hazard of his life. And ſuch effect hath this generall drinking in, or hearing of the word: But on the contrary, the particular plaiſter clapt on the particular ſoare doth worke the cure, if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be done. Now if in our naturall knowledge, and with our bodily eyes we can ſee this, let vs alſo in our ſpirituall knowledge, conſider that the diſeaſed and wounded ſoule is in like manner cured.</p>
            <p>The reading of the Scriptures with generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, admonitions, reprehenſions, exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſolations, I grant are moſt neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ground-worke and matter of the cure: but what ſound conuerſion is wrought thereby in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, without diſcreete application, let euery man that hath profited any thing in the ſchoole of Chriſt, be iudge. Put the caſe that ſome one of you had ſome hurt, or wound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or had ſome mortall diſeaſe reigning in you, would you not gladly haue the helpe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15390:6"/>
of the ſkilfulleſt Chirurgion, or Phyſitian, if you could? would you not redeeme your liues with the expence of your goods? What if when your Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian came vnto you, he ſhould begin to reade ſome part of <hi>Galen, Hypocrates,</hi> or other Phyſicke bookes, and to make a long diſcourſe of the foure Elements, with their properties, and qualities of the foure hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the body, and diſeaſes incident to man, with their remedies and cures, and ſo hauing taken your money ſhall take his leaue of you, ſaying that hee hopes you ſhall be as ſtrong and luſtie ere it be long as euer you were; what would you thinke or ſay of ſuch a Phyſitian? how well would you thinke your money beſtowed? If in caſe of your bodily health and welfare you would haue an honeſt, plaine-dealing, carefull and wiſe Phyſitian, that had not onely a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall knowledge of bodies diſeaſes and remedies, but that could moreouer apply and bend all his skill to the particular and liuely diſcerning of your body, of your diſeaſe, and of the particular cure of the ſame: yea, and if you will diſcouer, and ſhew vnto him the ſtate of your body to your vtmoſt knowledge for his further helpe and direction; how much more ought you to doe the ſame for your ſoules health? but moſt men are like to children, and fooliſh patients, that had rather die then drinke a bitter potion, or haue their ſoares launced and dreſſed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, particular application is neceſſary to bring vs to the knowledge of our ſelues, for natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are ſo blinded with ſelfe-loue, that howſoeuer we can diſcerne and iudge other men, and ſift them very neare, and too neare, yet when we come to looke into our ſelues, to take view and to make examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our owne knowledges, conſciences, hearts, affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, we finde all well, little or nothing amiſſe, wee haue enough to ſay for excuſe and defence of our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15390:6"/>
ſelues, if any obiection be made.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not this to open the mouthes of prophane perſons, which being partly phariſaicall, partly heatheniſh, count none hypocrites, but honeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours (I meane ſuch as feare God, and doe loue his word, receiuing the ſame with all willingneſſe and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and are louing and obedient to their Prince, and to all that are in authority, temporall, and eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall vnder him) becauſe they ſee ſome infirmities &amp; imperfections in them, being quick-ſighted enough to eſpie their leaſt infirmities, but lightly paſſe ouer all the vertues, gifts and graces of Gods ſpirit in them, like the bumble-Bee or Beetle, that flieth ouer all the pleaſant flowers, and lighteth on the horſe-dung, where ſhee maketh her aboad: but I ſpeake of the blindnes of mans corrupt nature, which raineth in the vnregenerate. An euident and plaine example hereof there is in <hi>Mathew.</hi> 23. 30. <hi>If we had beene in the daies of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 30.</note>
               <hi>our fathers, we would not haue beene partners with them in the blood of the Prophets.</hi> Theſe hypocriticall Phariſes condemne their fathers for murthering the Prophets; but they being blinded with their luſts, and ſelfe-loue, cannot diſcerne that they are worſe then their fathers, in that they goe about to murther the Sonne of God. Hereupon it commeth to paſſe, that the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, being of ciuill carriage and conformable to outward worſhip, are the greateſt iuſtifiers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, branding the beſt and moſt ſanctified men with notes of hypocriſie, aggrauating their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, miſtaking their deedes, miſconſtruing their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; whereof the holy man <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth; <hi>they daily miſtake my ſayings,</hi> whereby Ieſus Chriſt was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and condemned; whereby <hi>Elias</hi> was accuſed by <hi>Ahab</hi> to be the troubler of Iſrael, &amp; whereby <hi>Amos</hi> was accuſed by <hi>Amaziah</hi> to be a traitour againſt <hi>Ieroboam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, this blindneſſe preuaileth much oft times with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15390:7"/>
the godly, as here we ſee in the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> of whom God teſtified that he was a man according to his owne hearts deſire: though <hi>Nathan</hi> propounded his ſinne in a moſt plaine parable, in euery particular anſwerable and proportionable to his ſinne, which he could not in ſo ſhort a ſpace forget (eſpecially ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Bathſheba</hi> euery day in his ſight, which might occaſion him to remember his ſinnes) yet here wee ſee, hee is farre from making particular application thereof to himſelfe: yea, and is ſo blinded with ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, as that he vtterly condemnes that in another, the like whereof he approueth in himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing that you are as young children that cannot cooke, diuide, and cut their owne meate, it is neceſſary that the ſame be prepared for you by your ſpirituall nurſes, and fathers, if you deſire to reape any profit thereby. You ſee how the great world affords meate, drinke, and cloathes vnto you, and all things ſerue for no other vſe then the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the body, and maintenance of the perſon: and you ſee how all theſe things muſt paſſe through the hands of the Tradeſman &amp; Artificer, by whoſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and preparation they become meate, drinke and cloth. The corne in the field, and the beaſts of the earth, the fiſhes in the ſea, the foules of the aire, are no meate for you, the wooll on the ſheepes backes, the skinnes on the beaſts backes, the flaxe on the ſtalkes, are no cloathing; the trees in the wood, and ſtones in the earth, are no buildings, till they be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and wrought by the Craftſman or Tradeſman: euery one cannot worke and prepare them, but they that are called and appointed for the ſame purpoſe. And although euery man hauing the grounds of Art in him, may make a ſhift to feede, clothe, and build without the Artificer, yet it is but a bad and very meane ſhift, and as good as no ſhift in many things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15390:7"/>
This you ſee to be true in bodily things; euen ſo is it in ſpirituall things. The word of God contained in the old and new Teſtament, is the ſpirituall world, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all things neceſſary for the ſuſtenance and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the ſoule to eternall life therein contained. Theſe things muſt paſſe through the hands of Gods artſman, or tradeſman, who is to worke, prepare, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide and impart the ſame to euery one according to his eſtate, and want. You cannot ſerue your ſelues thereof, no more then the Eunuch could doe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Philip.</hi> Your Tradeſman, or Artificer, whom God hath called, muſt doe it for you: of him muſt you learne to ſerue your ſelues, as the childe learnes of the nurſe, and the Prentice of his Maiſter. Hence it is that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Timothy.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 15. <hi>Studie to ſhew</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 15.</note>
               <hi>thy ſelfe approued vnto God; a workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, diuiding the word of truth aright.</hi> And in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 10. Hee calleth himſelfe a skilfull maiſter <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 10</note>builder.</p>
            <p>If then in the preparation of bodily things we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a cunning and skilfull workeman that can handle his toole according to knowledge for our bodily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; how much more then skilfull Paſtours and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that can handle the word according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for the good of your ſoules, to feede you, to clothe you, to prepare, and fit you for Gods building.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſeeing that you cannot come to the knowledge of your ſelues without particular applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word, how ſhould any man come to true conuerſion? for if you haue not the knowledge of your ſelues in particular and ſpeciall, you cannot make particular confeſſion of your owne ſinnes, euen your perſonall ſinnes, whereby no other men but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you alone haue offended God, you cannot bee truely humbled for your ſinnes, hauing no liuely touch or feeling of ſinne; you cannot ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15390:8"/>
for ſo long as you ſhuffle in your ſelues with all, you will not repent till all repent: you cannot pray for graces neceſſary becauſe you know not your wants, being poore, and blinde, and naked, and yet thinking that you are rich; you cannot hunger and thirſt after Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe: you cannot be truely thankefull for the endleſſe loue, and mercy of God in your redemption, becauſe you know not what God hath done for you, in not knowing your owne ſinnes and miſerie: you cannot receiue true and ſound ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall comfort by the Goſpell, for want of knowledge, and feeling of your particular miſerable eſtate. Theſe things moſt neceſſary to bee done for your ſoules health, can ye not doe, vnleſſe all men doe the ſame, ſo long as you ſtand on generalities. Now all men will neuer doe theſe things, neither will you ſo long as you depend on this All.</p>
            <p>Nay further, the want of this knowledge of your ſelues, which by particular application of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture you muſt come to, will make you ſecure, vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, preſumptuous contemners of the word, and altogether irreligious: wherefore euery man in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ought to deſire perſonall application of the word, and to pray vnto God, that his Paſtour might ſpeake to his heart and conſcience, that he in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar might receiue inſtruction and edification by him, and that he might not goe away emptie, but returne bettered in knowledge and affection.</p>
            <p>It may be obiected, particular application is not for all Auditors, for ſome are ſo learned, and ſo wiſe, as when they heare the doctrine, they can make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication thereof to themſelues. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is one thing what they can doe, it is another thing what they will doe, and it is a third thing, what is our office and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of our duties. We may not preſume of other mens doings and neglect Gods commandements,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15390:8"/>
and the practiſe of the Prophets of Chriſt, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
            <p>Againe, men, euen the beſt men, will make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation generall, and fauourable enough to themſelues, hauing ſo many withdrawers, the continuall motions and ſurges of originall ſinne, the manifold allurements and prouocations of the euill world, the continuall ſuggeſtions of Sathan, implacable enemies of the beſt and moſt ſanctified men, ſo that although they be good ſeruants, and good ſchollers, they may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their duties without their maiſters euer and anone calling on them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point herein to be conſidered, is the perſon that is to make this particular application. The perſon is the Lords meſſenger, not ſpeaking from his owne ſpirit and affection, but ſhewing forth the vertue and power of the Lords ſpirit in him, as <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> ſaid, that <hi>which the Lord hath bid me to ſpeake, that will I ſpeake:</hi> And ſeeing that the Lord ſpeaketh by him, being a man of like nature and infirmities with his brethren; he muſt ſo ſpeake, and apply the word, as to his owne ſelfe amongſt the reſt (being no Lord ouer Gods heritage) vrging, and inforcing the word vpon the conſcience, as he doth the ſame vpon his owne; vrging the practiſe of Chriſtian duties vpon others, without ſhew of taking libertie to himſelfe; ſpeaking from a feeling in himſelfe, and ſhewing forth his loue of the godly, and his commiſeration and pittie of the hard hearted, after the example of our Sauiour Chriſt. <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. 5. he looked angerly on the <note place="margin">Mark. 3. 5.</note>Phariſes that watched him to enſnare him, but mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo for the hardneſſe of their hearts. Of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. Ier.</hi> 9. 1. <hi>Oh that my head were full of water, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9. 1.</note>
               <hi>mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night for the ſlaine of the daughter of my people.</hi> Of <hi>Paul. Rom</hi> 9. 3. He would redeeme the reiection of <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 2.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:15390:9"/>
the Iewes with his owne damnation. Otherwiſe, hee that vſeth the word deceitfully, ſeruing his owne turne therewith againſt his brethren, poyſoneth the pure word of God, with the corruption, and contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne humours and affections, and though he particularly apply the word, yet he profiteth his hearers nothing at all, neither to godlineſſe, nor mortification of ſinne, but rather foſtereth, cheriſheth, and incenſeth the ſame in his flocke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, that the heart of man anſwereth to man, as the face doth to the face in the water; the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and vnſanctified heart of the hearer to the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and vnſanctified heart of the ſpeaker; the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all heart of the hearer, to the ſpirituall heart of the ſpeaker: and the ſpirituall heart of the hearer hath a ſecret perceiuance in it, to diſcerne betweene the word comming from a ſanctified heart, and the ſame comming from a corrupt heart. Hence it is, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other reaſons, the ſame word taught by diuers men hath not the ſame effect in the hearer; for the Lord is powerfull by his word ſent by his owne meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and the ſame word brought by them that are not ſent, becommeth fruitleſſe.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Act.</hi> 19. 14. 15. 16. The ſeauen ſonnes of <hi>Scheua</hi> tooke vpon them to adiure euill ſpirits, by the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> whom <hi>Paul</hi> Preached: but the ſpirit anſwered; <hi>Ieſus,</hi> I acknowledge, and <hi>Paul</hi> I know, but who are ye? Here you ſee the euill ſpirit obeyed not thoſe coniurers vſing the name of Ieſus againſt them; and why? becauſe they were not ſent of God as <hi>Paul</hi> was, but being without faith vſe his name as it were to magicall inchantments. Therefore this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, vſed by <hi>Paul,</hi> being faithfull, and called, was of force to binde and caſt out diuels, but being vſed by them, being vnfaithfull and not called, is as a dead letter, or idle word; yea it hath a contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15390:9"/>
euen ſo wicked men in whom ſinne reigneth, and Satan worketh, deſpiſe the word preached, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hate the particular application thereof by them that are not ſent; for becauſe they vſe the word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully and politikely for their owne aduantage, it is not of force to expell Sathan, and to conuert the ſinner, but hath rather a contrary effect, namely, to harden them more, and to deſtroy the weake. An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample hereof we haue in the falſe Apoſtles of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth that preached the ſame doctrine of the Goſpell that <hi>Paul</hi> did, yet had it not the ſame effect, but ſtirred vp ſtrife, enuying, wrath, contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, back bitings, ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings &amp; diſcord; for though they were bigge in words, ſhewing learning and eloquence, yet had they not the power of the ſpirit in them, therfore their doctrine was but a dead letter. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 19. 20. <hi>When I am come I will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 19. 20.</note>
               <hi>know, not the ſpeech of them that are puffed vp, but the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for the kingdome of God is not in word, but in power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiection.</hi> The true and faithfull ſhepheard, that ſpeaketh in plaine euidence of the ſpirit is contemned and derided of the wicked many times, and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular applications are not onely vnprofitable for their conuerſion, but they haue power, like the m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n poſſeſſed with the euil ſpirit againſt him, to wound him and to ouerthrow him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this I briefely anſwere, that howſoeuer prophane, and irreligious perſons may perſecute the meſſengers of God with deriſion, railing or otherwiſe for his plaine and round dealing with them; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their ſpirits and conſciences conuince them of folly and obſtinacie, and telleth them that God ſpake to them by him, and that he doth faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcharge his dutie; and therefore they cannot but haue a feare and reuerence of his word, and of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, though they ſtriue with themſelues to doe the contrary; yea, and outwardly doe the contrary;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15390:10"/>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 46.</note> As for example, in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. 46. The officers of the high Prieſts and Phariſees came to apprehend our Sauiour Chriſt, but being come into his preſence and hearing his words, they had no power to take him, though they had a deſire to take him; but retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Ioh 18. 6.</note>this anſwere? <hi>Neuer man ſpake as this man doth. Ioh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 18. 6. When the band of men, with the officers of the high Prieſts came to take Ieſus, and he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming forth, ſaid vnto them, <hi>I am he,</hi> they went back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and fell to the ground: for theſe wicked wretches being conuinced of their owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, were not able to abide his preſence: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <note place="margin">Act. 24. 26.</note>the houre of darkeneſſe being come, they laid hold on him. In <hi>Act.</hi> 24. 26. wicked <hi>Felix</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled when he heard <hi>Paul</hi> diſputing of iuſtice, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and the iudgement to come; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he left him in bonds. And the Phariſees when they were in Chriſts preſece<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were touched with a ſence and perſeuerane of his godhead; therefore he charged <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 13. 32.</note>them with ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 32.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point then, the perſon that is to make this particular application of the word with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, is the true meſſenger of God, in whoſe perſon, behauiour, words and conuerſation of life, the ſpirit of ſanctification appeareth, which confirmeth the godly, comforteth and ſtrengthneth the weake, conuerteth the ſinner, bridleth the obſtinate, and ſtoppeth the mouth of the aduerſarie.</p>
            <p>The third point is, to whom this particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication is to be made. Application of the word is to be made to all men liuing, from the higheſt to the loweſt. The word of God is the rule of life, and euery man is to be guided and gouerned in minde, will, heart, affections, words &amp; works by the ſame, which he canot be without particular application thereof for his owne inſtruction in knowledge, and reformation in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15390:10"/>
for the word of God muſt not be made a vaine and idle ſtorie, no more then the Kings lawes are, ſeeing that it is the booke of ſpirituall life, for all men that looke to be ſaued, euen as the Kings lawes are the booke of temporall and ciuill life for his ſubiects. Therefore ſeeing that the life of the word ſtands in practiſe, and the practiſe of the word is our life, euen our ſpirituall and Chriſtian life; the application there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is moſt neceſſary for all men whatſoeuer, for inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, exhortation, admonition, reprehenſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiection.</hi> Who dare be ſo bold as to reproue great men, they haue vnderſtanding, knowledge and learning, therefore they neede not that any man ſhould inſtruct, exhort, admoniſh or reprooue them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Satan indeede by his meſſengers dare not admoniſh, dehort or reprehend great ones, becauſe it would hinder the building vp of his kingdome, and turne ſoules away from him; therefore doth he by his meſſengers ſooth and flatter them, as he did <hi>Ahab, Iezabell, Ieroboam:</hi> and ſuch like falſe Prophets there hath euer beene, and euer will be, which at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant of viſitation and deſtruction, ſhall crie, Peace, Peace; there ſhall be proſperitie, health, libertie and plentie, all ſhall be well. But contrarily the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords dare admoniſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort and reproue all men liuing in the world by his meſſengers: It is not they, but the Lord by his owne word that admoniſheth and reproueth, and who dare be bold to reſiſt the word of the Lord, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence the greateſt potentate of the earth is but duſt and aſhes? The wrath of the King (ſaith <hi>Salomon)</hi> is as the roaring of a Lion, much more the wrath of the Lord, who tormenteth not onely the body, but ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth body and ſoule into hell fire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15390:11"/>
Againe, where it is obiected that they haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, knowledge and learning, heare what <note place="margin">Ier. 5. 4. 5.</note>
               <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. 4. 5. <hi>Surely they are poore, they are fooliſh, for they know not the way of the Lord, nor the iudgement of their God.</hi> 5. <hi>I will ge<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mee to the great men, and will ſpeake to them, for they haue knowne the way of the Lord, and the iudgement of their God; but theſe haue altogether broken the yoake, and burſt the bonds a ſunder.</hi> Riches and honours are ſtrong temptors, and Sathan is there moſt buſie: therefore ſaith <hi>Salomon, let mee not be too rich, leaſt I forget thee.</hi> If Sathan be moſt buſie there, then the word of the Lord had neede to be moſt plentifull there; for Sathan neither can, nor will haue any nay, reſiſtance or reproofe, but by the word of the Lord; it is that onely that bindeth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, elſe bee will beare rule whereſoeuer hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</p>
            <p>Againe, where riches and honours are, there are, or at leaſtwiſe would be ſoothers and flatterers, <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziahs</hi> and <hi>Doeggs,</hi> Sathans inſtruments, and inueiglers to bend and turne riches, honours, power and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yea all gifts and bleſſings againſt God, againſt his Church, and the faithfull, that in the fall of them Sathans kingdome may be erected and ſet vp in the earth, who euer ſince the Lord threw him downe from heauen, ſeeketh like a rebell and vſurper to thruſt the Lord out of the earth, to which he layeth <note place="margin">Luk. 4. 6.</note>claime, and whereof he maketh open challenge, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>All this power will I giue thee, and the glory of theſe Kingdomes, if thou wilt fall downe and worſhip me;</hi> where he maketh himſelfe Lord and diſpoſer of the earth and all worldly things. Now if riches, honours and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be followed vpon with tempting <hi>Amaziahs, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eggs, Zedkijahs</hi> and ſuch like, if they ſee any way laid open for them, how great neede is there of the word Lord, and the particular application thereof in plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15390:11"/>
vprightneſſe, truth and ſinceritie, to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſophiſtrie, and particular temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than?</p>
            <p>Marke this one thing, Sathans word, to wit, his temptations and prouocations are very ſtrong and powerfull. For firſt, he deales with men in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Againe, he prouoketh them but to that to which they are themſelues inclined. Thirdly, his meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and all his inſtruments are deceitfull workers like himſelfe, cunning to humour, pleaſe, and to flatter men, thereby to blinde their eyes, and to corrupt their iudgements, that in doing euill they might not know what to doe. Now if we contrarily ſhall handle the word generally and doubtfully, and alſo mans nature being ſo blinded with ſelfe-loue, as it can make no vſe thereof for it owne conuerſion and reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what great aduantage giue we to Sathan? we ſhall ſtand as it were like fooles talking of by-matters, and pleaſing our ſelues with our prattle, whiles the old craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty foxe, the olde beaten ſouldiour, ſteales away Gods ſheepe (the ſoules committed to our keeping and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) out of our hands; whereas like faithfull ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards we ſhould giue him the encounter according to <note place="margin">Epheſ 6. 12.</note>the onſet, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6 12.</p>
            <p>Doth Sathan deale with men in particular to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them? how much more then ſhould we deale par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly with them (I meane not to particularite mens faults in publike) but in loue to giue priuate inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, exhortation, counſell, admonition, which is too little vſed now a daies; yea, we haue runne out ſo farre from that Antichriſtian auricular confeſsion as that we are fallen into the contrary extremitie, like them that auoyding the rocke <hi>Scylla,</hi> fall into the gulfe <hi>Charibdis,</hi> and as fooles, that ſhunning one vice runne into the contrarie vice, hauing no wiſedome nor diſcretion to keepe a meane: Euen ſo now is the whole worke of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15390:12"/>
Miniſterie in many places brought to a meere forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a generall and roauing ſermon on the Sabbath day, and what they haue heard they know not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can make any vſe thereof; but for any other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the people neither regard their Paſtour, nor the Paſtour the People, vnleſſe in Tithes gathering, and looking well to haue all his due; which (to ſay the truth) this deuouring and Epicuriſh age thirſteth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after, then after the foode of their ſoules. Sathan in theſe daies changing the ſheepe into wolues, as in former daies he changed the ſhepheards into wolues.</p>
            <p>Hereupon commeth this generall ignorance of the worke of the Miniſterie in moſt people: hereupon commeth the contempt of the perſon of the Miniſter: hereupon commeth this light regard of the word preached: hereupon commeth this petulancie, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneneſſe and wildeneſſe (as I may ſay) of young people, &amp; prophaneneſſe of old people of all ſorts; yea vpon this cauſe commeth this generall corruption of manners and Epicuriſh liuing.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point, if we doe conſider with our ſelues how the men of God dealt perſonally with Kings, Princes, falſe-prophets and Prieſts, as <hi>Eliah</hi> with <hi>Ahab, Eliſha</hi> with <hi>Iehoram, Ieremie</hi> with <hi>Paſhur, Amos</hi> with <hi>Amaziah, Micah</hi> with <hi>Zidkijah, Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt with <hi>Herod,</hi> our Sauiour <hi>Chrſt</hi> with the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees, Stephen</hi> with the high <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Elders, Peter</hi> with the people of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> with the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> and the ſame Apoſtle with <hi>Elimas</hi> and the high-<hi>Pieſt;</hi> we haue great incouragement, and confidence giuen vs to apply the Scriptures to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the times to the worlds end, which is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the true and profitable preaching, ſuch as the Lord hath commanded; yea if wee ſhall alſo conſider the plaineneſſe, vprightneſſe, ſobrietie, deuotion, humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and reuerence to Gods word of Chriſtians in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15390:12"/>
primitiue Church (comparing our ſelues I ſay with them) we ſhall finde our ſelues too generally to be but ſlippes and counterfeits, rather the Apes of good Chriſtians, then good Chriſtians indeede, being full of pride, diſſimu ation and craft, commonly tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med pollicie; full of intemperancie, mockers of true deuotion, ſtubborne and wilfull, full of ſubtiltie to ſerue our owne worldly turnes and vſes, of the word it ſelfe. But if we compare our ſelues with our ſelues, theſe foule corruptions in theſe latter times will little appeare to vs, ſeeing that in theſe daies we can ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly varniſh ouer, yea beautifie ſinne with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Chriſtianitie and heatheniſh ciuilitie. And this is the cauſe why the common ſort ſo call for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but loue not to heare the law, their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences foaming vp mite and durt which the world ſees not, and becauſe the hard heart will not humble it ſelfe to walke with God, being of vnbridled affections; therefore it ſeekes for falſe comforts, ſoothings and flatterings in the Goſpell (the leauen of malice not being purged out) the law being a bondage to them and a heauie burthen, whereas it is a law of libertie to the Godly: and for the deeper blinding and hardning of themſelues, they lay falſe imputations vpon the true and plaine-dealing Shepheard, as raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, indiſcretion, too much ſtricktneſſe and preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, affectation of ſingularitie, phantaſticalneſſe, by which tearmes they ſhew themſelues like to the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and earthly Edomites (for ſo the word ſignified) which vnder the title of circumciſion, and the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> claimed to themſelues the chiefe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and hated the true worſhippers. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 7. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 137 7.</note>
               <hi>the children of Edom O Lord, in the day of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, how they ſaid downe with it, downe with it, euen to the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth point herein to be obſerued, is how
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15390:13"/>
this particular application ought to bee taken. It ought to be taken as the word of the Lord, and therefore in good part, whether it be with vs or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Luk. 4. 22. 28</note>vs, howſoeuer phariſaicall people, that are like the <hi>Nazarens, Luk.</hi> 4. 22. 28. doe heare the word applied, not as the word of God, (as indeede it is) but as the word of man, contrary to the practiſe of <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2. 13.</note>the faithfull <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 13. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſaid well (had they done as well) to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 42 6.</note>
               <hi>Ier.</hi> 42. 6. <hi>Whether it be good or euill, we will obey the voice of the Lord, to whom wee ſend thee, that it may be well with vs, when we obey the voice of the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the further explication hereof, there are but two ſorts of people, ſome good, ſome bad, ſome ſheepe, ſome goates: The ſheepe doe heare and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 27.</note>the voice of the ſhepheard. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. 27. the goatiſh heare with the outward eare, but they goe away into ſtrange waies and vneuen by-paths. Now as touching the word and the particular application thereof, the wicked in ſome things agree with the godly, in ſome things they differ.</p>
            <p>Firſt ciuill wicked men, whoſe liues and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions are according to their owne hearts luſts, can ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well abide doctrines and generall diſcourſes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe which flow with humaine learning and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, for there the naturall eare findeth ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to feede vpon.</p>
            <p>Againe the wickedeſt man can indifferently abide two particular applications, the firſt is of inſtruction, for inſtruction preſuppoſeth vertue, and ſtirs vp to good life, which the worſt would gladly haue the name of, and ſo for praiſe and reward-ſake will liſt to it: the ſecond is of comfort, and preaching of peace, which none will refuſe.</p>
            <p>But here is the difference, when we come to make
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15390:13"/>
vſe of the doctrine, to conuincement of ſinne, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, and to correction, the hard-hearted and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinner will at no hand abide it; ſuch words ſound in his eares like <hi>Micahs</hi> in <hi>Ahabs, neuer good.</hi> Herein they differ from the godly, and leaue them alone to themſelues. Now begin they to ſhew their goatiſhneſſe, to accuſe their ſhepheards of indiſcretion, of malice, of priuate grudge, of beleeuing falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, of particularizing and naming men in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, when there is no ſuch matter intended or thought vpon, and therefore they cannot with a patient eie euer after looke vpon him.</p>
            <p>But contrarily in whom there is the loue and feare of God, and the hatred of ſinne, which haue denied themſelues and worldly luſts, and warring againſt their ſpirituall enemies, do deſire the particular application of the word, that their conſciences, hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may be wrought vpon in particular, that they in particular may be ſtirred vp and awaked, leaſt they fall into the deadly ſleepe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>This particular applying ſtrengthneth them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageth them, and keepeth the enemie a farre off, it weakeneth him, and daunteth him. This application is as the trayning of Chriſtian ſouldiers, and as it were a ſtanding by them to tell them how to ward the ſtroke, and to giue the ſtroke, to auoide the aſſault, and to giue the onſet. We are ſluggiſh, ſleepie, heauie, our eyes are euer downe, I meane our mindes and affections are euer on the earth and earthly things; we haue neede therefore not onely to be called on, but oft times to be rouzed, iogged, pulled by the armes, and to be fet on our feet, for as much as that originall corruption, the world and the diuell, are euer giuing vs <hi>Opium</hi> to drinke, that cauſeth deadly ſleepe, if we take too much of it.</p>
            <p>The godly that are growne to ſome good meaſure
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15390:14"/>
of perfection, for theſe reſpects, as alſo that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that God alone may be glorified in the earth; and for the loue they beare to all men, doe deſire both conuincement, reproofe and correction of ſinne in time and ſeaſon conuenient: and they alſo that are as yet but weake, yet true Chriſtians, can with patience abide the word as well againſt them, as with them. And how harſh, and diſtaſtfull ſoeuer it be vnto them; yet doe they not caſt it off, nor hate their paſtours, no more then gratious children caſt off their parents admonitions, counſels and commandements (though in moſt things they be not to their liking;) or doe run from them when they are reproued or corrected: though lewd ſeruants and wicked children doe ſo, yet the louing childe and good ſeruant will not. As for example: <hi>Dauid</hi> in his place; being reproued by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and hauing heauie iudgements denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him for his ſinnes, what doth he? fals hee to excuſing, defending and mittigating of his ſinne, like <hi>Saul,</hi> and turning it lightly off as but an infirmitie, as many mockers doe now a daies? Doth he ſcorne, grudge at and reuile the Prophet? Doth he accuſe him of pride, impudencie, or indiſcretion, or too much boldneſſe for dealing thus plainely with the King? No, but being ſtroke with feare and reuerence of the true word of the Lord, with compunction and ſorrow for his ſinne, he maketh humble and penitent confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion before the Lord, in <hi>verſe</hi> 13. <hi>I haue ſinned againſt the Lord.</hi> The like penitent, and humble anſwer gaue the good King <hi>Ezechiah</hi> to <hi>Eſay, chap.</hi> 39. reproouing him for ſhewing ambitiouſly and vaine-gloriouſly all the treaſures of his kingdome to the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Babilon,</hi> and alſo threatning the iudgements of God vpon him in his poſteritie for the ſame: <hi>The word of the Lord,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>is good, which thou haſt ſpoken.</hi> Wherein he ſheweth his humilitie to the word, his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitencie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15390:14"/>
for his ſinne, and thankefulneſſe to the Lord for ſparing him till his ſonnes daies. In the 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 18. When <hi>Samuel</hi> had told to <hi>Ely</hi> the iudgements which God had threatned to bring vpon him and his houſe for euer, for not chaſtning his ſonnes wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, his anſwere is in penitencie and humilitie; <hi>It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good;</hi> and this hath beene alwaies the practiſe of the godly, with penitent, meeke, humble and obedient hearts to yeeld themſelues to the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now on the contrary, the wicked will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, reuerence, or regard the word of God no further then they may make vſe of it for their owne carnall turnes, and ſo farre forth as it is agreeable to them, otherwiſe they reiect it as ſuperfluous and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable for them. When the word, by the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, like a ſoueraigne ſalue begins to worke vpon the conſcience, heart, affections and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, for their true and ſound conuerſion, then begin they to ſhew forth the ſtubborneneſſe, rebellion and hypocriſie that lay hidde in them, vnknowne to others, and euen to their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull hearts.</p>
            <p>So long as the word concernes all, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular none, they acknowledge it to be the word of God, but when it comes to be applied to the heart and conſcience in particular, then it is the word of man: the Preacher ſpeakes them of malice, of ſome falſe information, of his owne vncharitable diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of indiſcreete zeale, or from a phantaſticall ſpirit, nothing can pleaſe them; hee muſt walke wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hee had neede to be as wiſe as the Serpent, and as innocent as the Doue, neither for all that can hee eſcape mockes, by-words, or one diſgrace or other. Examples hereof wee haue in <hi>Ier.</hi> 43. 2. 3. <hi>Then ſpake Azariah, Iohanan, and all the proud men,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15390:15"/>
ſaying to <hi>Ieremie, Thou ſpeakeſt falſely: the Lord our God hath not ſent thee to ſay, goe not into Aegypt to dwell there.</hi> 3. <hi>But Baruch the ſonne of Neriah prouoketh thee againſt vs,</hi> &amp;c. In the former chapter they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched <hi>Ieremie</hi> to pray to the Lord for them, that the Lord might ſhew vnto them the way wherein they might walke, and what they ſhould doe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, yea, taking God to witneſſe that they would doe whatſoeuer the Lord commanded them by him.</p>
            <p>Now after ten daies the word of the Lord came to <hi>Ieremie,</hi> which <hi>Ieremie</hi> faithfully declared vnto them: That if they would dwell in their owne land, the Lord would build them, and not deſtroy them, plant them, and not roote them out, that he would be with them, to ſaue and deliuer them from the hand of <hi>Pharao,</hi> but if they would goe into <hi>Aegypt</hi> for ſafetie and protection, that then the ſword, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and peſtilence which they ſo feared ſhould ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take them. Now they hearing the commandement of the Lord to be contrary to their plot which they had laid already, and preferring their owne deuiſes and pollicies before the Lords will, they begin to finde excuſes and delayes, thereby to ſhufle off, and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the commandement of the Lord, as plainely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in theſe two verſes before alleadged. Wherein obſerue, firſt that Hypocrites determine with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues what they will doe, and how, and after what manner they will liue, euen according to their owne iudgements, and after the imaginations of their owne hearts: and then in the ſecond place, they will heare what the Lord ſaith. Now that which they thinke to be agreeable to them, they praiſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and approoue as the word of GOD; but when it diſſenteth from them, and is contrary to their owne liking, when it conuinceth, reproueth or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15390:15"/>
toucheth them (as we ſay) then it is the word of men, and not the word of the Lord: And for this purpoſe they haue excuſes, arguments and reaſons at will, for the confirming and hardning of themſelues in their owne courſe and trade of life. Secondly, obſerue herein that pride of heart is the cauſe of rebellion and contempt of the Miniſter, and conſequently of the Lord in his perſon, in theſe words <hi>(And all the proud men.)</hi> Thirdly, obſerue the qualitie of ſecret hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, when it is plainely and directly conuinced and reproued in particular, it breaketh forth into open rage, laying imputations on the Miniſter, for the excuſe &amp; hiding of it ſelfe, in theſe words, <hi>[Thou ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt falſely.]</hi> Fourthly, obſerue that Hypocrites will be counted good Chriſtians, and call God their God, and yet will deſpiſe their Paſtours, and contemne the word of the Lord ſpoken by them, <hi>(The Lord our God.)</hi> Fiftly, note the nature of Hypocriſie, they would obey God, and embrace his word, if they were ſure that his meſſengers ſpake truth: whereas indeede they are farre from all obedience, <hi>(hath not ſent thee.)</hi> Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, note the common ſlaunders and imputations of common Hypocriſie, <hi>(But Baruch</hi> &amp;c.) Another plaine example hereof there is, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 8. <hi>Iehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> being to fight againſt the King of <hi>Aram,</hi> for <hi>Ramoth Gilead, Iehoſaphat</hi> prayed him to aske counſell of the Lord; and ſo <hi>Ahab</hi> gathered together foure hundred falſe Prophets, which agreed all in one tale: For this is the reſolution of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry falſe Prophet, to pleaſe; But theſe Prophets <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> much regarded not, therefore hee aſked if there were neuer a Prophet of the Lord; yes, ſaith <hi>Ahab,</hi> there is yet one man, <hi>Micah the ſonne of Imlah,</hi> but I hate him, for hee neuer prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied good vnto mee. Likewiſe in <hi>Amos.</hi> 7. <hi>Amos</hi> hauing propheſied deſtruction to the wicked King
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15390:16"/>
               <hi>Ieroboam</hi> for his Idolatrie and other ſinnes that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the ſame; the couetous King <hi>Amaziah</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth him ſecretly to the King of conſpiracie, but when by that way hee preuailed not, he aſſayed by another practiſe to ſtoppe his mouth, in the 12. and 13. verſes. A notable example hereof alſo there is in <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. the <hi>Nazarens</hi> could willingly here our Sauiour Chriſt reade his text out of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and interprete the ſame Scripture of himſelfe; but when he came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue them for their infidilitie, and preferreth ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers before them, that ſhould beleeue in him; they were preſently incenſed with wrath and great indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and carried him out of the citie to the top of a rocke to caſt him downe headlong.</p>
            <p>Furthermore it was the common practſe of the rebellious <hi>Iſraelites</hi> alwaies to lay ſlanders and falſe imputations vpon the true Prophets, and to tearme them falſe Prophets. If they propheſied of peace and proſperitie, then they generally beleeued them, and if ſome one or few were doubtfull or diſtruſtfull, yet they would not count them falſe Prophets; but if they conuinced them or reproued them for ſinne, denouncing vengeance vpon them vnleſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, then on the contrary, generally they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them falſ-Prophets, hauing them, mocking them, giuing them by-words, impriſoning them, ſtoning them, excepting ſome very few.</p>
            <p>If the falſe-Prophet ſpake of peace, victorie and proſperitie, and the ſame came not to paſſe, yet they were not puniſhed (though by the law they were commanded to ſtone ſuch to death:) but when the true Prophets ſpake of Gods iudgements for their ſinnes, they were out of hand and without any delay perſecuted, impriſoned, murthered before the time of their triall came. As I <hi>King.</hi> 22. 27. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> muſt be kept in priſon, and fed with the bread
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15390:16"/>
and water of affliction till <hi>Ahab</hi> returne from victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; becauſe hee propheſied deſtruction; but the foure hundred falſe-Prophets were at libertie both then and after. They dealt ſcornefully and cruelly alwaies with the Prophets of the Lord, but the lying Prophets and flattering couetous Prieſts wanted no preferment, fauour, nor countenance, though their flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries were neuer ſo groſſe and palpable.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
